

🛮 (+44) 7459-023461 | 🗷 contactnuhuibrahim@gmail.com | 🖸 nuhu-ibrahim | 🛅 nuhu-ibrahim | 💆 @_Nuhulbrahim

"Driven by code, fueled by creativity, and dedicated to transforming possibilities into reality."

Summary.

Nuhu Ibrahim is a resourceful, hardworking software engineer and team leader who has worked with reputable software and hardware development companies, government agencies and companies and over two dozen clients worldwide with a result-delivery mindset. He is passionate about the automation of IT processes.

Education

The University of Manchester, England

Distinction (85%)

MSc in Advanced Computer Science with Specialisation in Artificial Intelligence

September 2020 - October 2021

- Thesis: Automatic Detection of Deaths from Social Networking Sites. Published at Information Management and Big Data Conference, 2021.
- · Modules: Text Mining, Computer Vision, Data Engineering, Systems Governance, Querying Data on the Web, Modeling Data on the Web.

Ahmadu Bello University, Nigeria

First Class - CGPA 4.94/5.00 (99%)

BSc (Hons), Computer Science

October 2015 - November 2018

- Thesis: "NaijaPeopleRep": Bridging the gap between Nigerians and their representatives.
- <u>Modules:</u> Data Structures & Algorithms, Design & Analysis of Algorithms, Systems Analysis & Design, Software Engineering, Formal Methods in Software Engineering, Advance Database Management, Object Oriented Programming and Web Development, Linear Algebra, Numerical Analysis, Probability and Statistics, and Mathematical Methods.

Kaduna Polytechnic, Kaduna - Nigeria

Distinction - CGPA 3.51/4.00 (88%)

ND. COMPUTER SCIENCE

November 2011 - October 2014

 Modules: Object Oriented Programming, Linear Algebra, Discrete Structures, Web Development, Computer Application Packages, Introduction to Computing and Computer Architectures.

Experience

Fiserv Inc.

London, United Kingdom

DEVELOPMENT TEAM LEAD, PLATFORMS

March 2021 - Present

- Spearheaded the development and contributed significantly to the architectural design of a financial transaction monitoring engine for facilitating and managing merchants and consumer risks on payment transactions using rule-based approaches.
- Maintained and improved the efficiency and scaling of the company's Exchange platform for transaction processing to accommodate significantly more merchants.
- Participated in the integration of faster payments to the company's Exchange platform.
- · Completed all projects and fixed all bugs within deadlines, securing at least 90% client and development manager's satisfaction scores.
- Followed Agile development methodology (Scrum), including requirement gathering, impact analysis, and sprint planning to find solutions for all business needs and translate requirements into functional and technical specifications.

Kaduna State Government Kaduna, Nigeria

SPECIAL ASSISTANT TO SENIOR ADVISER & COUNSELLOR

August 2019 - October 2020

- Proposed a strategic and data-centric platform to visualize economic growth, revenue generation and job creation.
- Designed, developed and deployed websites for Kaduna State Government companies and agencies.
- Collaborated with various stakeholders, including the government ministries, agencies, and departments, private sector entities, and community representatives, to identify bottlenecks and develop innovative solutions to ensure that the Kaduna State Government remains top in all Ease of Doing Business (EoDB) rankings.

The Penetralia Hub

Abuja, Nigeria

REMOTE SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (PART-TIME)

August 2019 - October 2020

- Built an employee management application to manage employees' records, attendance, leave, salaries, projects, tasks and appraisals, which is now used as an enterprise software solution across multiple companies and organisations.
- Developed a fully functional web-based tax portal for Nasarawa State Internal Revenue Service, Nigeria, that significantly reduced tax evasion
 in the state by over 5%.

Lexington Technologies Kaduna, Nigeria

SOFTWARE ENGINEER January 2019 – August 2019

• Led a team to develop the Nigerian Academic Research Intelligence System (NARIS), a plagiarism detection software that is being adopted by Federal Universities in Nigeria.

• Deployed an academic repository titled "the Nigerian Academic Research Repository (NARR)" set to be implemented as a centralised repository for research contents in Nigerian Universities, Polytechnics, Colleges of Education and Research Institutes.

Dixre EnterpriseKaduna, Nigeria

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER (INTERNSHIP)

- December 2015 November 2018
- · Spearheaded communication with client to understand pain points. Increased customer retention by 17%.
- Developed the company's management software that provides detailed and concise information on the company income, expense and revenue generation.
- Managed training for the organization's newly hired employees attached to the software development team.

Guaranty Trust Bank Kaduna, Nigeria

CUSTOMER SERVICE REPRESENTATIVE (INTERNSHIP)

February 2015 - September 2015

- Developed relationships with at least 90 new customers and typically increased customer satisfaction and retention.
- Answered an average of 20 questions daily about account types and banking products.
- Successfully trained and coached a replacement after securing admission to study for a degree program in Computer Science.

Research and Publications ___

Natural Language Processing (NLP), Text Mining and Computer Vision

- <u>Ibrahim, N.</u>, & Batista-Navarro, R. (2022). Automatic Detection of Deaths from Social Networking Sites. In Annual International Conference on Information Management and Big Data (pp. 236-252). Springer, Cham.
- Coutinho, J. et al. (2021). Social Media Opinions on Tokyo Olympics during the COVID-19 Pandemic. Manuscript submitted for publication.
- Ibrahim, N. et al. (2021). Deep learning methods for Questions Classification. Unpublished manuscript, The University of Manchester, Department of Computer Science, Manchester, England.
- <u>Ibrahim, N.</u> (2021). Face Recognition: Survey. Unpublished manuscript, The University of Manchester, Department of Computer Science, Manchester, England.

Technologies Summary & Stack _____

Java, JavaScript, PHP, Python

STACK SUMMARY

- Java/J2EE: Spring MVC, Spring Framework, Spring Integration, Spring Batch, Spring Cloud, Maven, Helm Chart, Kubernetes, Docker, Kafka, RabbitMQ, JavaSE and JavaFX.
- PHP: Laravel, Codelgniter, Symphony, PhalconPHP, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, VueJS and NuxtJS.
- JavaScript: Node.js, VueJS and JQuery.
- Python: Arduino, OpenCV, scikit-learn, Keras and Pytorch.
- <u>Database:</u> MySQL, MongoDB, Postgres, Redis and GraphDB.
- Infrastructures: Digital Ocean, AWS, Cloudflare, GCP, Git, etc.

Honors & Awards

2017	Most Impactful Student, Department of Computer Science, ABU Zaria	Zaria, Nigeria
2018	Faculty Overall Student, Dean's annual prize, Faculty of Physical Sciences, ABU Zaria.	Zaria, Nigeria
2018	Gold Medalist (1st Winners), 7th Nigerian Universities Computer Programming Contest (NUCPC)	Abuja, Nigeria
2019	Best Graduating Student, From one of the best 5 Universities in Nigeria	Lagos, Nigeria

Program Committees

2017	President, Ahmadu Bello University Developers (ABUDevs) Club	Nigeria
2018	Association Software Director, National Association of Computer Science Students (NACOSS)	Nigeria
2018	Organizer & Host, ABUDevs Hackathon and Idea Pitch	Nigeria
2019	Organizer & Keynote Speaker, Google Developers Group (GDG) DevFest	Nigeria

Hobbies and Interests

Swimming, football and badminton.